And we praise the Lord for that and understand the importance of living a life of surrender.
If you have your Bible with you this evening, the book of Revelation, we'll look at chapter number 7 this evening.
But before we get really all the way into chapter 7, we'll be looking at a couple of different places.
And so hold your place here in Revelation 7.
And as you're there, I want you to also take and look over at Matthew chapter 24.
Matthew chapter number 24 this evening. And so we'll look at Matthew 24 and Revelation chapter number 7.
And then if you have the ability to have a third spot, you'll be in Habakkuk chapter number 3.
And we do sword drills in teen Sunday school class.
And every time I do one of the minor prophets, the young people are like,
where's that one? Where's that one? You know, and they're trying to find it.
And so that's always exciting. And we thank the Lord for the word of God.
And so we'll begin looking in Revelation chapter number 7. Revelation chapter number 7.
I'm just going to read the first few verses of Scripture.
And then we'll make some comments and some comparisons, looking at some other portions of Scripture here,
before we dig into the entirety of chapter 7.
Notice the Bible says in verse number 1 of Revelation 7,
And after these things, I saw four angels standing on the four corners of the earth,
holding the four winds of the earth, that the wind should not blow on the earth, nor on the sea, nor on any tree.
And I saw another angel ascending from the east, having the seal of the living God.
And he cried with a loud voice to the four angels to whom it was given to hurt the earth and the sea,
saying, Hurt not the earth, neither the sea, nor the trees,
till we have sealed the servants of our God in their foreheads.
And I heard the number of them which were sealed, and there were sealed,
and hundred and forty and four thousand of all the tribes of the children of Israel.
Now we'll look at the entirety of the chapter this evening.
But I believe as we begin looking here at Revelation chapter number 7,
that it would be helpful to have a quick review of kind of where we are in the book of Revelation,
and kind of what's gone on.
Remember that the book of Revelation, really unique to the book of Revelation,
it provides for us an outline for the book within itself.
In Revelation chapter 1, in verse 19, it says,
Write the things which thou hast seen, part 1, and the things which are, part 2,
and the things which shall be hereafter, part 3.
Now part 3 of the book of Revelation starts in Revelation chapter 4.
And so we find that the things that he's seen would be Revelation chapter 1,
the things which are would be Revelation 2 and 3,
the letters to the seven churches.
And then starting in chapter number 4 would be the things which shall be hereafter.
Now you'll recall with me, and we've labored through some of these things,
as you begin looking and studying through the book of Revelation,
you're reminded that there are varying scenes, transitional type scenes, if you will,
alternating scenes, where you'll see some things that are taking place on earth,
while there's other things that are taking place in heaven.
And then there's also some parenthetical, or some interludes, if you will.
And Revelation chapter number 7 happens to be one of those interludes,
one of those parentheticals.
And so really, as we look at chapter number 7,
the narrative of the book isn't like moving forward.
It's just a parenthetical, kind of like when we looked at Revelation 4,
in chapter number 5 specifically, when you're in that scene,
that throne room of heaven, and you see what's happening,
and God's giving us that revelation.
And so as we look at chapter number 7 again this evening
and understanding where we are,
we've gone through that first scene in heaven, chapters 4 and 5,
and then we came back to looking at what was taking place on earth
with the start of the tribulation in Revelation chapter 6,
and we find that the tribulation begins with the seal judgments.
And when we look at chapter number 6,
we study through six of those seal judgments,
and I have you in Matthew chapter 24,
because it's very interesting to see the parallel, or the correlation, if you will,
between what we read in the first several verses of Matthew 24
and what we've studied in the previous weeks
dealing with the seal judgments of Revelation chapter number 6.
And so in Matthew chapter 24, beginning in verse number 1,
I want you to actually, we're going to look at verse number 3 is where we begin.
Matthew chapter 24 and verse number 3,
and notice what the Bible says,
the question is asked, and he says,
He sat upon the Mount of Olives.
The disciples came unto him privately, saying,
Tell us, when shall these things be?
And what shall be the sign of thy coming and of the end of the world?
Now understand, the book of Matthew is written predominantly to a Jewish audience,
and it's important for us to understand that as we interpret Matthew chapter 24.
There's been many that have gone astray in trying to interpret Matthew 24
with regard to eschatology,
and they kind of get all messed up with the timing of things.
And we understand that, yes, Jesus is coming for his saints, the rapture,
and then Jesus is coming with his saints.
That's the true second coming of Christ in Revelation chapter 19.
He's going to put his foot on the Mount of Olives.
It will be split asunder.
And, of course, the Battle of Armageddon and so on and so forth will take place.
And so we see those two events.
And so when they ask the sign of thy coming and the end of the world,
he's not speaking in Matthew 24 about the rapture.
He's talking about the return of Christ at the end of the tribulation.
And it's interesting because you begin reading in verse number 4,
the Bible says, And Jesus answered and said unto them,
Take heed that no man deceive you.
Now isn't that interesting that that's where Jesus begins the answer to these disciples,
that they ask him in verse number 3 that question of what shall be the sign of thy coming
and of the end of the world.
And he says, the beginning of the answer, Take heed that no man deceive you.
And then in verse number 5, he begins to talk about, he says,
Look, for many shall come in my name, saying, I am Christ, and shall deceive many.
And we see how the truth of verse 4 and 5 of Matthew 24
really relates to the first seal judgment, the white horse.
Remember that white horse is antichrist.
And we find that the white horse will come and that's antichrist.
And so you see the relation here between Matthew 24 verses 4 and 5
and then Revelation 6 verses 1 and 2.
In verse number 6 of Matthew 24, And ye shall hear of wars and rumors of wars.
See that ye be not troubled, for all these things must come to pass,
but the end is not yet.
The second horse, that rider, is riding on a red horse in verses 3 and 4.
And what is that seal judgment? It's war.
Again, we've looked at these things the last several weeks,
looking at the book of Revelation and several lessons of these seal judgments.
And chapter number 24 and verse number 7,
For nation shall rise against nation and kingdom against kingdom.
Notice it says, And there shall be famines and pestilences and earthquakes in diverse places.
And the third of those seal judgments is the black horse, which is famine.
And then in verse number 8, And these are the beginning of sorrows.
And so again, that's the very beginning of the tribulation period.
The tribulation period known as the time of Jacob's trouble.
God is dealing with Israel specifically.
And so you see in verse 7 and 8 this death that would come
and that would be correlating to the fourth seal judgment,
that pale horse which brought death.
And then it's interesting because in verse number 9 it says,
Then shall they deliver you up to be afflicted and shall kill you
and shall be hated of all nations for my name's sake.
And then shall many be offended and shall betray one another and shall hate one another.
And you see in verse 9 and 10 there the martyrs, those that would be killed.
And you look at the seal judgments, the fifth seal judgment,
Revelation 6 verses 9 through 11 is that of the martyrs.
And then you look and you see the worldwide chaos.
And it's what we dealt with last week on the sixth seal judgment.
And when we looked at that judgment, we considered the catastrophic events,
but then we also considered the chaotic response.
And we find that it says that verse 11,
And many false prophets shall rise and shall deceive many.
And because iniquity shall abound, the love of many shall wax cold.
But he that shall endure until the end, the same shall be saved.
And so again, we begin to see the correlation between Matthew chapter 24
in these first 13 verses and Revelation chapter number 6.
As we begin to enter into the seventh chapter,
it's interesting because in verse 14 of Matthew 24, the Bible says,
And this gospel of the kingdom shall be preached in all the world
for a witness unto all nations, and then shall the end come.
So the gospel of the kingdom is very specific
with regard to what's going to happen in Revelation chapter number 7.
We're going to look at that in just a moment this evening.
And as you continue reading through Matthew 24,
you find in verse 15, he says,
Many therefore shall see the abomination of desolation.
Now help me this evening. When does that take place?
The abomination of desolation takes place when?
The midpoint of the tribulation.
Daniel chapter number 9 gives abundantly clear details
with regard to the 70 weeks and all that's going to happen
in that 70th week and the peace treaty that will be established.
with Antichrist in Israel, and then how it's breached,
it's broken at that midpoint, and he comes in,
and he demands worship, that's the abomination
of desolation, and that's why it specifically says here,
spoken of by Daniel the prophet, stand in the holy place,
whoso readeth, let him understand.
And so again, we begin to notice here the correlation
between what we see in Matthew chapter 24
and the teaching of Jesus, and what we're looking at
here in Revelation six, and in chapter number seven.
So we look in chapter number seven of the book
of Revelation, we really see two categories of people,
we're gonna break it up into three particular points
and make some comments, but the two main groups
of people that you see in Revelation chapter number seven,
in the first eight verses, you see the Jewish people,
the Bible says there's 144,000, and the Bible says
that they're sealed on earth, and then you find
that as you look at the latter part of the chapter
in verse nine through 17, you'll find that that's given
to providing us with a record of that second group
of people, which is Gentiles from all nations,
without being numbered, in fact, it says,
which no man could number, and they're standing
at the throne, and so we see some distinctions here,
we're gonna deal with some of the truth
that God gives us here, and as we begin to look at this
and understand, I've titled the message specifically
from Habakkuk three in verse number two,
in wrath, remember mercy.
Now, as you look here in Revelation six,
remember, we finished up looking at the sixth seal
last week, and we talked about all of that
just catastrophic destruction that would come
and all the things that transpired, and we began to look
at the chaotic response and what the people do,
they hide what they say, what they believe,
and remember, they said, this is the wrath of the lamb,
but then we finished the message and really spent
quite a bit of time dealing with what we noticed
was missing, and that was that there was no repentance,
there was no brokenness, and of course,
we looked at that from Revelation chapter number six,
but then also made application for our own lives
and how we need to be broken over our own sin,
and there needs to be repentance, but it's interesting,
in verse number 16 of Revelation chapter number six,
it says, and said to the mountains and rocks,
fall on us and hide us from the face of him
that sitteth on the throne, and from the wrath of the lamb,
for the great day of his wrath has come,
and who shall be able to stand?
Chapter seven, after these things, I saw four angels
standing on the four corners of the earth,
and we're gonna go through this in just a moment,
but I want you to notice verse number three specifically,
I wanna draw your attention to what the Bible says.
In verse number three, it says this other angel
that's mentioned in verse number two says this
to those four angels, hurt not the earth,
neither the sea, nor the trees,
and then there's a little word there, till.
Till we have sealed the servants of our God
in their foreheads, in wrath, remember mercy.
I'm so thankful that our God is merciful.
I'm so thankful, we mentioned this morning about his grace,
and as we look at the text of scripture,
and we begin to understand what's unfolding,
we see first of all, if you're taking notes,
I want you to notice the angels in the first few verses.
Now, I've read through it a couple of times,
but I want you to notice what the purpose,
initial purpose of these angels would be.
According to verse number one,
you find that the Bible says that these four angels
were standing on the four corners of the earth.
Now, that's not to support some idea
of a flat earth perspective, and by the way,
that teaching is becoming more prevalent.
And surprisingly, Isaiah makes it very clear
that the sphere of the circle of the earth,
and it's really talking about just the distance
and kind of the four corners, we'd use that terminology,
and so he says here, notice,
holding the four winds of the earth,
and then he says that the wind should not blow on the earth,
nor on the sea, nor on any tree,
and then this other angel he saw descending from the east,
having the seal of the living God.
Now, we're gonna make note of that in just a moment,
but he cried with a loud voice to the four angels,
and then notice this phraseology,
to whom it was given to hurt the earth and the sea.
So really, these four angels,
as we begin reading in chapter number seven,
there's judgment that's going to come.
Now, there's seal judgments,
and then there's gonna be trumpet judgments,
and then there will be the vial or the bowl judgments,
and we see that throughout the book of Revelation
with these repeated judgments,
but we notice here that between the seals and the trumpets,
the trumpet judgments will begin in chapter number eight,
and between that, we have this interlude,
and we find that these four angels,
it's said there in verse number two,
to whom it was given to hurt the earth and the sea,
and then in verse number three, it says,
hurt not the earth, neither the sea, nor the trees,
and so we find that there was judgment
that was this impending judgment that was coming,
but we find that there was this till,
there was something that had to happen,
and it's very important that we see how God is working
and how he is in control of all things,
and he causes this really pause, if you will,
with regard to the judgment.
Now, we notice that it says in verse number two
that that angel, this other angel
that John saw from the east,
he had the seal of the living God,
and then it says in verse number three,
till we have sealed the servants of our God
in their foreheads, and so these servants
that we're gonna look at in just a moment
that are outlined for us in Revelation chapter number seven
are gonna receive a seal, and that seal
is gonna provide them with a measure of protection
during the judgments.
Now, that's exciting for us.
The reason it's exciting for us
is because we've been sealed as well, all right?
Now, this is a different seal than what we have,
but we find that there's this seal.
He calls it the seal of the living God in verse number two,
and he's gonna seal the servants of our God
in their foreheads.
Now, we understand this is a great contrast
to the mark of the beast that's outlined
in Revelation chapter 13, verses 16 and 17,
because everything that the Antichrist does
is in direct violation of what God does.
It's a counterfeit, and so there's this seal
that's placed upon these servants of God,
and then later on in the tribulation,
the Antichrist is going to give this distinction
with regard to this mark of the beast.
It's not the same seal.
It's not the same mark.
It's extremely distinct, and it's important
that we understand that, and so we notice
as we look at these 144,000,
we'll deal with them in just a moment,
but I want you to just pause and think about the fact
that the Bible says that they're going to be sealed,
and so what these angels were going to do,
what their duty was, they were put on pause
until these 144,000 could be sealed.
Hold your spot here and look at Ephesians chapter number one.
In Ephesians chapter number one,
God talks to us about our own position in Christ
and our salvation, and we find that there's a whole lot
of things that happened at the moment
in which you trust that Christ is your savior
and I trust that Christ is my savior,
and as we look here throughout the portion of scripture,
we find this great truth with regard to the fact
that we have been sealed, so notice with me
in verse number 13 of Ephesians chapter number one,
the Bible says, in whom ye also trusted
after that ye heard the word of truth,
the gospel of your salvation.
I'm gonna pause there, I'm gonna finish the verse
in just a moment, but aren't you thankful
that you heard the gospel?
Aren't you thankful that somebody was faithful
to preach the gospel, amen?
There was somebody somewhere in your life
and in my life that had to be obedient
to the instruction to preach the gospel to every creature,
and I'm not sure who it was in your life,
and we may not know each other's life story
as to who it might be, so I was born in a Christian home
and you gotta go a generation beyond that
and find out who it was that brought the gospel
to your family.
There's a man by the name of Kurt Branch
that God used to bring the gospel to my dad,
and I'm thankful for his obedience to preach the gospel,
and I heard the gospel, and after I heard the gospel,
notice where he says in verse 13 to begin it,
in whom ye also trusted after that ye heard.
The Bible tells us that we need to hear the gospel,
but you know the reality is that not everyone
that hears the gospel believes or receives,
and I'm thankful this evening to be part of that company
that's trusted the Lord Jesus Christ as my personal savior.
The Bible says that he came to his own,
his own received him not, but as many as received him,
to them gave he power to become the sons of God,
even to them that believe on his name,
and so as we look here and begin to understand,
I'm so thankful to be saved by the grace of God,
and I've trusted Jesus as my personal savior,
and it says in whom also, look at the rest of verse 13,
in whom also after that ye believed,
ye were sealed with that Holy Spirit of promise.
Isn't that a blessing?
We look at Revelation 7, and we look at the seal.
for these 144,000, but we must be mindful this evening
that as New Testament believers, we have been sealed.
And I'm so thankful to have the Holy Spirit.
I mentioned this morning at the end of the message
from James chapter number four,
that we have all of the Holy Spirit
and the Holy Spirit wants all of us.
And that's an appropriate idea.
Listen, remember what he said
in 1 Corinthians chapter number six,
you're bought with a price.
He bought me completely, amen?
And I'm thankful for that and I belong to him
and he has every right to want all of me and all of you.
If you buy something and you go to the store,
you go over there, you go to the lunch this afternoon,
you buy an entree and it comes to the table
and there's a bite missing out of your entree,
how are you gonna feel about that?
You'll be like, whoa, something,
I'm sending this back to the kitchen
and the waiter's like, no, I just wanted a part of it.
No, no, no, I paid for the whole thing, man.
That's a silly illustration, but we get the point.
I'm thankful to be sealed.
And notice what it says,
sealed with that Holy Spirit of promise.
And then in verse 14, which is the earnest
of our inheritance until the redemption
of the purchased possession under the praise of his glory.
Now, I am bought with the precious blood of Christ
and if you're saved, so are you,
but the reality is that we're not yet
in his presence and glory.
This mortal shall put on immortality,
this corruption shall put on incorruption.
We're gonna go be with him, 1 Thessalonians,
that we're gonna meet him in the clouds
if we're here during the rapture
and we'll be with him forever and hallelujah.
We're excited about that.
But we find that it says that it is the Holy Spirit
that we're sealed with that Holy Spirit of promise,
which is the earnest of our inheritance.
And so we have an inheritance.
According to 1 Peter, when you look there,
sorry, 2 Peter, when you think about the inheritance
that we have that we're sealed and that inheritance,
I said first and I said second, it's actually first.
1 Peter chapter one and verse four,
to an inheritance incorruptible and undefiled
and that fadeth not away reserved in heaven for you.
I have an inheritance.
And it says that the Holy Spirit who seals us,
which is the earnest of our inheritance,
we use that word earnest oftentimes
in the idea of real estate.
And you think about down money, earnest money.
And that's a small portion of the full price, right?
You put down that earnest money.
And so we find that we are sealed
and we ought to rejoice in that this evening.
And so we find as we begin reading Revelation chapter seven
and we're noticing what's taking place
and we see these angels and kind of what they're doing
and what their activity is,
but we're also reminded when we read about the fact
that they're sealing these servants of God
in their foreheads that we have been sealed
with the Holy Spirit of promise.
The second point this evening, we see the angels.
Notice the 144,000.
Now in chapter number seven of the book of Revelation,
we find in verses three through eight
that God tells us about these 144,000.
There's absolutely no reason that we should not believe
that this is exactly the number, that it is literal.
We interpret the Bible literally.
And we find that there have been many
that have taken this portion of scripture
and have misapplied and misinterpreted
who the 144,000 might be and where they are
and all of that sort of thing.
But God tells us exactly who they are.
And notice it says in verse number three,
it refers to them as the servants of our God.
And we find again, as we look there in the beginning
at Matthew chapter 24, and we made note there
with regard to those that would go out
in Matthew chapter 24, in the gospel of the kingdom
shall be preached in all the world
for a witness unto all nations and then shall the end come.
And so these 144,000 are referred to
as the servants of God.
Again, their number in verse four.
And I heard the number of them which were sealed
and there were sealed and 140 and 4,000
of all the tribes of the children of Israel.
It begins to go through and tell us
that there's 12,000 from each tribe.
It says in verse five of the tribe of Judah
were sealed 12,000, the tribe of Reuben were sealed 12,000,
the tribe of Gad were sealed 12,000,
the tribe of Asher were sealed 12,000,
the tribe of Nephthilim were sealed 12,000
and the tribe of Manassas were sealed 12,000.
Verse seven of the tribe of Simeon were sealed 12,000,
the tribe of Levi were sealed 12,000,
the tribe of Issachar were sealed 12,000,
the tribe of Zebulun were sealed 12,000,
the tribe of Joseph were sealed 12,000,
the tribe of Benjamin were sealed 12,000.
It's very interesting as you go through here,
we find that 12,000 again from each tribe,
we see the 144,000.
We'll see them again in Revelation chapter 14
in the first few verses
and I'll just read verse number one of Revelation 14.
It says, and I looked and lo,
a lamb stood on the Mount Zion
with him and 140 and 4,000,
having his father's name written in their foreheads.
And so we saw the seal in verse number three,
we see the 144,000.
Now we understand as we look here,
if you studied through, you read these verses of scripture
that the tribe of Dan is not mentioned.
There's many thoughts with regard to why that might be
and some have given the idea that Dan is not mentioned
because Dan was often associated
with a lot of the idolatry
that took place in the northern kingdom
and you think about they went up there
and set up all of that false worship and what have you
and a leader of idolatry.
But it's also interesting when you look here at the list
that instead of it, oftentimes when you read through
the list of the tribes of Israel,
you'll see Ephraim and Manasseh.
And here you don't see Ephraim mentioned,
you see Manasseh but you see Joseph.
And that's not typically the way
in which it's listed out.
And to add another detail, if you look at Ezekiel 48,
which we won't go there and look,
but you'll find that Dan is actually included in Ezekiel 48
and you say, pastor, what does all that mean?
I have no idea.
I'm just gonna be honest with you.
I got no idea.
But God does, amen.
And if you know, you let us know.
I just really don't, there's some theories,
there's some ideas, but I don't wanna give you
just my opinions.
I honestly just do not know with definitive certainty
why it is that they're listed the way that they are.
But I believe God and I believe there's a reason for it.
And then let me say this, before anyone gets excited
about the fact that there are lost tribes
and there's an inability for people to really be able
to know their lineage, et cetera, et cetera,
you remember that God is in control.
And so those that would have this idea,
man, there's these lost tribes
and no one really has the records
that they can't prove their lineage and so on and so forth.
God knows, and he says that these angels
are going to seal these servants of God in their foreheads
and they're gonna be 12,000 from each tribe.
And I'm just gonna trust that God
is going to get that right.
Is that good?
Amen, because our God do with all things well.
And if he says, it doesn't matter if we say,
humanly speaking, well, the British Empire,
they destroyed all the records
and there's all these lost tribes.
Man, that is human reasoning.
That removes God from the equation.
And I serve a God who knows everything,
is in control of everything,
and he's able to do exactly what he said he would do.
Amen, and so we see these 144,000.
The Bible doesn't tell us specifically
in these verses of scripture that they are the ones
that are gonna preach, as we mentioned in Matthew chapter 24
but it does lend our, we are understood
as we look at Matthew 24, it lends itself
with looking at the correlation
in the first several verses of the chapter
to what we read in Matthew 24 verses one through 13
with Revelation chapter number six,
and you see that direct correlation
that then when you see the gospel of the kingdom
being preached and then you see these 144,000,
it seems very obvious that that is the activity
that they would be engaged in.
Remember also that the tribulation period specifically
is with God dealing once again with his people Israel
and it's called the time of Jacob's trouble.
As we conclude the chapter verses nine through 17,
the third really kind of group of people, if you will,
if you think about the angels and then the 144,000,
in chapter seven verses nine through 17,
we see number three, the great multitude,
the great multitude.
Now we mentioned briefly a few weeks ago
part of this portion of scripture
as it related to the fifth seal
from Revelation chapter number six with those martyrs
and I made the distinction we spent some time
dealing with tribulation saints in that particular message
and I said this as we looked at that portion of scripture
that it's important for us to recognize this evening
that there will be lost people
that will enter into the tribulation
that had truly never heard the gospel
and there are lost people that will enter
into the tribulation period
and there will be preaching that will take place.
Not only here the 144,000 but there are two witnesses
that will begin in just a little bit
looking at their ministry and so we understand
people will be saved during the tribulation.
Now according to the book of Second Thessalonians,
if someone heard.
the gospel and rejected the gospel, then they will believe a lie and they will not be saved,
according to 2 Thessalonians chapter 2.
But as we look here in Revelation chapter 7 and we see this great multitude, notice
as John is describing this scene, he says in verse number 9,
Now we find in verse number 14, the Bible says, we're going to read all the verses in between,
but it says, look at verse 13,
And so one of the elders is asking John, who are these people?
And notice John's response,
Sir, thou knowest, isn't that a good answer?
In other words, he says, I have no idea, but you do.
Amen.
And so what happens, the elder answers and he says this,
These are they which came out of great tribulation and have washed their robes and made them white
in the blood of the Lamb.
Therefore are they before the throne of God and serve him day and night in his temple,
and he that sits on the throne shall dwell among them.
So we understand this multitude, this scene in heaven in Revelation chapter 7 is different
than what we read in chapter 4 and 5.
In chapter 4 and 5, you see the four beasts, you see the 420 elders, and we've went through
that, we've studied through that, understanding how those 24 elders represent the church age,
saints, so on and so forth.
And we understand all that's taking place.
And we see that even in chapter number 5, there's great worship that takes place.
And it's a great scene in heaven and all of the worship and praise that's taking place.
But when we come to chapter number 7, this is a different group of people.
These are the tribulation saints.
And notice it says in verse number 9, it's important that we see two factors that are
given to us in verse number 9 with regard to this great multitude.
Number one, it's innumerable.
Praise God for that.
I'm so thankful that God's grace is sufficient.
I'm so thankful that God's grace is abundant.
And I'm thankful that God is not willing that any should perish, but that all should come
to repentance.
And I'm thankful that it's unlimited.
Amen.
And what a blessing and innumerable.
He says a great multitude, which no man could number.
But I also want you to see that it's global.
I'm thankful that Jesus died for the sins of the world.
Amen.
And we think about this.
It says of all nations and kindreds and people and tongues, they stood before the throne
over there in chapter number 5.
We read about how that there was just this great group of people in chapter 5 and understanding
all that was taking place and understanding it says out of that has redeemed us to God
by thy blood out of every kindred and tongue and people and nation in verse number 9 of
chapter number 5.
But this is a different group of people.
And as we think about this global idea, when the Bible tells us specifically the details
of all nations and kindreds and people and tongues.
That's why we have missions to take the gospel to the whole world.
Amen.
And I'm thankful to be involved in the work of missions.
I'm thankful to be able to see what God is able to do through the work of our missionaries.
Every time we get a prayer letter and we read about souls that are being saved and lives
that are being changed, man, it encourages me.
I am thankful to hear about that.
To hear about that.
There's a lot of places on the on planet Earth today where people are much more receptive
to the gospel than they are here in Northern Virginia.
I mean, it's amazing how people are getting saved and people are responding and it's
exciting and that God would use us.
We think about the congregation and the size of our congregation, and we find that even
as the songwriter said, little is much when God is in it.
And you begin to think about the way that God would allow us as a congregation to be
engaged and involved with supporting so many missionaries.
There's an emphasis on it.
We place an emphasis on purpose.
Why?
Because our God is a global God.
And we see it here in Revelation chapter number nine in this scene that God gives us.
And we notice that it's innumerable.
It's a global perspective.
We ought to say hallelujah.
We ought to praise the Lord for that.
And then we begin to notice their praise and their worship.
Notice in verse 10 down through verse number 12, it says, and cried with a loud voice saying
salvation to our God, which sitteth upon the throne and unto the Lamb.
And all the angels stood around about the throne and about the elders and the four
beasts and fell before the throne on their faces.
And notice it says and worshiped God.
Here's what they said, according to verse number 12.
Amen.
Blessing and glory and wisdom and thanksgiving and honor and power and might be unto our
God forever and ever.
Amen.
I mean, they're just worshiping God, just praising God.
And here's what I've learned.
The Bible tells us that we're to stand in awe of Him.
And as I study the scriptures, I read the Bible, as I learn more about God, it leads
us to worship God, for He is worthy.
And we stand in awe of Him and we find that these tribulation saints, that they're there,
they're gathered around this great multitude and these really it's a multitude of Gentiles
and they're worshiping God and they're crying out.
The Bible says with a loud voice.
I know I've said it before, but I'm thankful when we sing that we sing with a loud voice.
I'm not talking about yelling and I'm not talking about carnality and I'm not talking
about all that kind of nonsense.
But I'm saying, listen, we got something to sing about.
Amen.
You ever drive down the road and those guys are playing some kind of music next to you
like, listen, I don't want to hear what you're playing, man.
And it's like rock in my car and it's nonsense.
Right.
You ever experienced that?
Listen, we have something exciting to sing about.
We sing those great hymns of the faith and you stand up and you sing and you begin to
think about what God has done for you and what that song is teaching us.
Man, it's exciting.
We worship through our singing.
Understand this evening that the song service in a church is not just a filler.
It's not just a filler.
It's worship.
So I don't sing real good.
That's OK.
Make a joyful noise unto the Lord.
Amen.
And praise the Lord.
I'm serious.
We might not ask you to sing a solo.
I've not been asked to sing a solo.
Amen.
But I sing with a loud voice.
I make a joyful noise unto the Lord.
Why?
Because he's worthy.
And it's not just a filler.
The time of singing is not just something that's like, well, you know, get this ready, do this,
finish that.
No, no, no.
We come in, we're prepared to worship.
And I'm telling you, you know what happens when we're singing those songs?
Not only is God glorified, but our hearts begin to get prepared for what we have that
we're going to open from the word of God and feast on manna from heaven.
And man, it's exciting.
And we see that they're worshiping God.
We're going to worship him for all of eternity.
Amen.
He is worthy.
And that's why we got to learn to worship him here on earth.
Amen.
And by the way, David says, come, let us worship.
Right.
And you begin to think about, let us magnify the Lord.
Let us exalt the Lord.
And we begin to understand this evening that we're to lift our voice and we're to worship
God in the midst of the congregation of God's people, but also in the midst of the heathen.
They need to know how good our God is because our God's a great God.
We noticed some specific things that are mentioned with regard that would give us
insight to their identity.
I've already read verses 13 and 14, but then also some details that are provided that are
of interest.
Notice, we find that that elder speaks with John and ask the question, what are these
which are arrayed in white robes?
And whence came they?
And John says to him, sir, thou knowest.
And he said to me, these are they which came out of great tribulation, have washed their
robes and made them white in the blood of the lamb.
Therefore, are they before the throne of God and serve him day and night in his temple,
and he that sitteth on the throne shall dwell among them.
Then notice verse 16, very interesting verse of scripture.
The Bible says this, they shall hunger no more, neither thirst anymore, neither shall
the sun light on them, nor any heat.
So it seems, as you read verse 16, that these are things that these tribulation saints experienced.
Because God specifically says of these ones that are tribulation saints, according to
verse 14, that they shall hunger no more.
So that would reveal to us that they were hungering, right?
And it says that they shall, look again, it says neither thirst anymore, neither shall
the sun light on them, nor any heat.
So these.
These are things that these tribulation saints experience
through their time of going living through the tribulation
and various aspects of what takes place.
And notice, and we're gonna look at these things
as we move on through the study in the book of Revelation,
but look at Revelation 13 and verse number 17.
Now, we understand this is with regard
to the mark of the beast.
And notice one of the things that is going to be required.
They caused them, according to verse number 15,
and he had power to give life unto the image of the beast,
that the image of the beast should both speak
and cause that as many as would not worship
the image of the beast should be killed.
And he causeth all, both small and great,
rich and poor, free and bond, to receive a mark
in their right hand or in their foreheads.
And that no man might buy or sell,
save he that had the mark of the image of the beast
or the number of his name.
Now, I believe that if these people are saved,
they're not gonna get the mark of the beast.
And so if you're saved and you don't get the mark
of the beast, and in order to buy, sell, or trade,
you have to have the mark of the beast,
guess what you're gonna do?
You're gonna hunger.
And so God says, they shall hunger no more.
Isn't that precious?
And we see in chapter 16, when you think about that idea
that they'll thirst no more, in chapter 16,
and there's some other verses you could look at
with regard to this one, with regard to thirsting,
because there's many judgments that are poured out
upon the waters of the earth.
But look specifically at Revelation 16,
in verse number four, it says,
and the third angel poured out his vial
upon the rivers and fountains of water,
and they became blood.
So if you're living during that time,
guess what you're gonna do?
You're gonna thirst.
You remember what happened in Egypt?
The waters returned to blood, that was a problem.
Right?
And so we see here that it says,
they shall hunger no more, neither thirst any more,
neither shall the sun light on them, nor any heat.
Now that's also a very interesting aspect
from Revelation chapter 16.
We looked at it in verse number four,
but look at verses eight and nine.
This is the fourth bowl judgment, or vial judgment,
and it's interesting because it says
that what this angel's going to do
during this fourth vial judgment,
is it says he's gonna pour out his vial
upon the sun, and power was given unto him to what?
To scorch men with fire.
And men were scorched with great heat,
and blaspheme in the name of God,
which hath power over these plagues,
and they repented not to give him glory.
So you see that idea that he was gonna,
that that fourth vial judgment
is power to scorch men with fire.
Notice what God says specifically in chapter seven,
in verse 16, neither shall the sun light on them,
nor any heat.
I don't think that's carrying with it the idea
that they're not gonna see the sun anymore.
It's about the judgment that's associated
with that fourth vial.
And so to begin to look at this and understand,
and begin to see what's happening,
we rejoice in knowing in chapter number 20,
in verse number four of the book of Revelation.
Now to kind of fast forward,
as we look at the timeline, if you will,
when we come to Revelation chapter number 20,
the tribulation is over, all right?
The Lord has come back, we've come back with him.
As I often joke, that's the next time I'll ride a horse,
is Revelation 19, amen?
Praise the Lord, and so will you.
And you say, I like to ride horses every week.
The Lord bless you, you'll ride it on that day as well.
And you'll just have a little more experience than I will,
but I'll be in a perfect situation,
and I'll be able to ride that thing just fine.
And we'll come back with Jesus,
it'll be the battle of Armageddon.
And then you come into chapter number 20,
and you begin to see about the millennial reign of Christ.
And before that millennial reign,
we understand that Satan is going to be bound
for a thousand years.
But then look at verse four of Revelation 20,
and I saw thrones, and they sat upon them,
and judgment was given unto them.
And I saw the souls of them that were beheaded
for the witness of Jesus and for the word of God,
and which had not worshiped the beast,
neither his image, neither had received his mark
upon their foreheads or in their hands,
and they lived and reigned with Christ a thousand years.
And it said in Revelation seven, in verse number 15,
therefore, are they before the throne of God
and serve him day and night in his temple,
and he that sitteth on the throne shall dwell among them.
And then verse 16, we read a moment ago,
but verse 17, for the lamb,
which is in the midst of the throne,
shall feed them and shall lead them
unto living fountains of waters,
and God shall wipe away all tears from their eyes.
I believe that's not gonna happen
just for the tribulation saints,
but for all of us in Revelation chapter 21
in verse number four makes mention of that
with regard to really thinking about
the great white throne judgment that ends chapter 20,
and then how he wipes away all the tears,
and what a blessing that is.
And as we look through this chapter
and begin to see the different,
the angels, the 144,000, the great multitude,
and understand some of the distinctions
that God has given to us,
and we rejoice in understanding
that our God is in control,
and our God is merciful,
and our God is gracious,
and listen, there's nothing that's beyond
the control or power of our God,
and it says there in verse number 17
that he's gonna feed them,
lead them unto living fountains of waters,
and he'll wipe away all tears from their eyes,
and I'm thankful that we belong to him, amen?
Now, we're not tribulation saints, all right?
We're part of the church age,
and I'm thankful for that.
There's a distinction, right?
We've looked at that, we've understood that,
we've talked about that a few different times,
and we see the distinction scripturally,
but we can rejoice in knowing that in every age
there are people that will be saved by grace,
and I'm thankful for that, and it's a blessing.
Now, we have a job to do.
A few lessons ago, it was more than a few weeks,
but a few lessons ago,
I preached on one of these sealed judgments,
and I just used the word throughout
the entire message of urgency, urgency.
When we read of these events in the book of Revelation,
and I'm gonna summarize this quickly,
when we read of these events in the book of Revelation,
they're going to happen,
and I don't know exactly when they're gonna happen,
but I know the event that starts the clock, all right?
So, the clock has been stopped, if you will, right,
between the 69th and 70th week of Daniel
because we have the church age,
and we don't know exactly how long the church age is,
but Jesus does, the Lord knows,
and the clock is going to restart at the rapture.
You don't know when the rapture's gonna be,
and neither do I, and there is urgency
that is needed on the part of God's people
to do the work that God has called us to do.
These things are going to happen,
but God's left us instructions for what we're to do today,
to redeem the time, right?
That's a responsibility.
What happened in the church of the Laodiceans,
they got, man, they were just indifferent,
they were apathetic.
Mark preached, taught a great lesson on apathy
for our men's meeting a couple of weeks ago,
and listen, we, unfortunately, when you're filled
like they were there, the church of the Laodiceans,
and you have increase of goods
and have quote-unquote need of nothing,
the reality is that we can get really apathetic.
You know what I think has happened?
In America, amongst Christianity,
is we've gotten really apathetic.
We've gotten really comfortable with the things
that we have and the pleasures of this world.
We really have, and there's a need for urgency
amongst the people of God.
People are dying, people are dying.
There has been eternity somewhere.
There's only two places, there's only two places, right?
We believe that biblically,
and if they die without Christ,
they'll spend eternity in the lake of fire.
There must be urgency on the part of God's people.
Let us pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for loving us.
Thank you for the word of God.
God, we don't understand every detail,
even as I admitted this evening,
but we know that you do and we trust you.
God, as we see these records that are provided for us,
we can take pieces and rejoice in seeing what's accomplished
and how you're working,
reminds us of not only what you're going to do
in a future day,
but reminds us of what you want to do in this day.
And God, I pray that as much as we'd like to learn
and be equipped with regard to eschatology in a future day,
would you help us not to lose sight of this day?
Would you help us to live this day with urgency?
Would you help us to fulfill what you've called us to do?
I pray that you would use us, God,
for your honor and for your glory.
I pray that in the moment of invitation,
that you'd help work in hearts and lives only you can,
and we'll thank you for it.
In Christ's name we pray.
Would you stand with me?
And Kimberly's gonna play quietly on the piano,
and maybe you just wanna come and thank the Lord
for what he's revealed to us,
but also maybe ask the Lord to help us
to have that present tense urgency.
Yes, there's some things that God's going to do
in a future day, and we can rejoice in that,
but what is God doing in this day?
As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.
["God Rest Ye Merry Gentlemen"]